we're starting a new section of this
video series where we talk about Le
groups and Lee algebras and how they
relate to
Spinners in particle physics we classify
particles according to their fundamental
properties such as mass and electric
charge one important fundamental
property is the particle spin which is
either an integer or a half
integer all known fundamental particles
have spins of either zero 1 half or one
for spin zero we have the higs Bon for
spin 1/2 we have the matter type
particles like quarks electrons and
neutrinos and for spin one we have Force
carrying particles like photons gluons
and the w and z
bosons the value of a particle's spin
determines how we describe it in a
mathematical equation spin zero
particles are represented by scalers
spin 1/2 particles are represented by
Spinners and spin one particles are
represented by
vectors the spin value is sort of like
the rank of the tensor used to represent
the particle scalers are rank zero
tensors vectors are rank one tensors and
Spinners Loosely speaking are kind of
like rank 1/ half tensors since they
rotate half as much as vectors do when
transformed is it's also possible to
combine fundamental particles into
composite particles which can have
higher spins like three
halves these particles are represented
by higher dimensional objects that are
tensor products of spinners and
vectors the hypothetical graviton is
Spin 2 and this is related to the fact
that the metric tensor from general
relativity is a Rank 2
tensor so what does this have to do with
Lee algebras and Le groups well it's
important to know how a particle will
behave when we do a physical
transformation like a rotation or boost
the various different particle types
will transform with different types of
matrices for example in 3D vectors will
rotate in the XY plane using this Matrix
and Spinners will rotate in the XY plane
using this
Matrix scalers can be thought of as rot
ating with a 1 by one Matrix containing
the number one this basically means that
scalers don't change their value in
different rotated coordinate
systems we say these matrices belong to
Le
groups in mathematics a group is a set
of elements that can be combined
together and Obey certain properties
such as having an identity element and
inverse elements that undo
transformations since we can combine two
rotations into another rotation rotate
by 0 degrees to get the identity Matrix
and take the inverse of rotation
matrices to undo rotations sets of
rotation matrices form a group a Le
group is a group that's continuous
instead of discret reflection
Transformations are not a Le group
because they involve discrete jumps but
rotations are a Le group because we can
smoothly move from a small rotation to a
large
rotation every Lee group has a
corresponding Lee algebra which is a
special set of matrices that we can
exponentiate to get Le group
matrices understanding these Lee
algebras can tell us a lot about how to
transform various kinds of
particles and all the different types of
quantum operators and quantum mechanics
belong to various Lee
algebras so let's start off by trying to
understand how to take the exponent of a
matrix this 3x3 Matrix here gives us a
rotation in the XY plane by an angle
Theta this Matrix is a member of the Le
group SO3 the special orthogonal 3x3
matrices which do rotations in
3D orthogonal means the matrix's inverse
is its transpose and special means the
Matrix determinant is + one
now it turns out that this rotation
Matrix is equal to the exponential of
theta times this special 3x3 Matrix here
the Matrix in the exponent is called a
generator and is a member of the Lee
algebra s SO3 which is written with
lowercase letters in a fractor font by
convention so how do we make sense of
this what does it mean to take the
exponential of a
matrix the answer lies in the tailor
series of e to the X normally this is
used when X is an ordinary number but we
can replace x with a matrix M to give us
this definition of a matrix's
exponential while this gives us an
infinite Series in our example The
Matrix Powers will form a repeating
pattern so we actually only need to
evaluate the first few Powers so let's
evaluate the first few powers of the
Matrix M and what we
get for M the 0 we're going to say that
any Matrix to the power of 0 gives the
identity Matrix similar to how any
number to the power of0 gives
1 m to the 1 is just the Matrix M
itself to calculate m^ 2ar we just do M
* m and we get a matrix with the entries
- 1 0 01 in the top left corner and all
the other entries are
zero m 3 just gives M * m^ 2 and after
multiplying this out we find the result
is
M M 4 is m 3 * m which is just m * m or
m^
2 and it turns out that M 5 after using
some of the identities we've discovered
is just m so this is where the cycle
starts repeating in the tailor
Series so we take m to the 0o to be the
identity Matrix and the next four powers
of M just repeat in a cycle
forever so let's take the first few
terms in our infinite series and plug in
these Matrix
Powers let's focus on adding together
the entries in the top left corner of
the Matrix we see this gives us the
tailor series for cosine of
theta look looking at some of the other
entries we get more tailor series for
negative sin Theta sin Theta and cosine
Theta and the bottom right corner of the
Matrix is just one because of the one in
the identity Matrix at the start of the
series so after using a few tricks with
the tailor series we can indeed see that
this Matrix exponential gives us a 3X3
rotation Matrix in the XY
plane so we know that when we
exponentiate this generator Matrix times
an angle we get a rotation Matrix in the
XY plane but how did I know to use this
generator Matrix
specifically it turns out that there's a
straightforward recipe to go from a Le
group Matrix to its Lee algebra
generator let's say that we have e to
the S Theta where s is just a number if
we take the derivative with respect to
Theta a factor of s comes down in front
by Chain rule next if we set Theta to
zero the exponential goes to one and
we're left with just s so to isolate s
we use two steps take the derivative
then set the parameter to zero this
recipe works in the case of a matrix
M2 taking the derivative with respect to
Theta brings a copy of M down in front
you can try proving this by taking the
derivative of the exponential series if
you like next next setting Theta to 0
means e to the 0 Matrix which becomes
the identity Matrix so we're left with
just the Matrix M which is our generator
Matrix so the recipe for getting our
generator Matrix m is to take our
rotation Matrix R in the Le group take
its derivative and then set the
parameter to
zero let's try this out on our XY
rotation
Matrix taking the derivative with
respect to Theta SS become cosiness and
cosiness become negative SS and in the
lower right corner the derivative of the
constant 1 is
0 then we set Theta to 0 S of 0 gives 0
and cosine of 0 gives 1 so we end up
with the generator Matrix I showed
earlier in the video as
expected you can pause the video and
show that these rotation matrices in the
y z and ZX planes give these generator
matrices from now on I'm going to denote
the generator matrices as gxy gy Z and
gzx which generate the rotations in the
XY y z and ZX planes
respectively this is getting a little
off topic for this video but it turns
out you can also take the exponential of
a derivative operator using the tailor
series
definition if we multiply this
derivative by a parameter a and
exponentiate it the resulting operator
is a machine that translates a function
by some amount a you can pause the video
if you want to read the full proof of
this so just as these 3x3 matrices
generate rotation matrices on 3D vectors
when
exponentiated this derivative operator
generates a translation operator on
functions when
exponentiated this is related to why the
momentum operator in quantum mechanics
contains a derivative because momentum
is the generator of
translations and it uses the complex ey
to ensure the operator is her Mission I
won't say any more about that in this
video but I've left some links in the
description to videos that go into more
detail now let let's get back to our SO3
generator
matrices it's worth looking at these
generator matrices and seeing if they
have anything in common it turns out
that the generator matrices of SO3 are
all traceless so the sum of their
diagonal elements is zero and anti-
symmetric so their transpose equals
their
negative we can go ahead and prove this
to prove the traceless property I'm
going to start with this theorem which
says that for a matrix a the determinant
of e to the a is equal to e to the trace
of a this is easy to prove if a is a
diagonal matrix where its igen values
are along the
diagonal in this case e to the a just
means taking the exponential of the
individual diagonal
elements and the determinant of this
Matrix would just be the product of the
diagonal
elements on the other hand the trace of
a is just the sum of the diagonal
elements and if we exponentiate this sum
we see it is equal to the determinant we
calculated before if we use basic
exponent
rules now this proof only works for
diagonal
matrices but since I values the
determinant and the trace of a matrix
are unchanged by a change of coordinates
this proof also works for any Matrix
that is diag
ionizable our SO3 generator matrices are
diagonalizable and so the corresponding
rotation matrices are also
diagonalizable provided we allow for
complex Matrix
entries so the theorem we discussed
earlier also works for our rotation
matrices and their
generators as an exercise you can try to
figure out why the rotation Matrix and
its generator transform using the same
coordinate change Matrix c as a hint
remember to look at the Taylor series
definition of Matrix
exponentiation so using this theorem and
knowing the determinant of an SO3 Matrix
is + one we can write the rotation
Matrix in exponential form use the
theorem to rewrite it as the exponential
of the trace and since this exponential
equals 1 for all Theta we must conclude
that the trace of the generator m is
zero so we've proven that SO3 generator
matrices are
traceless now let's prove s SO3
generator matrices are
anti-symmetric we know that for an SO3
Matrix are its inverse equals its
transpose so R * R transpose equals the
identity
Matrix now let's take the derivative of
both sides on the left side we use
product rule to get a sum of two
products and on the right the identity
Matrix is a constant so its derivative
is the zero
Matrix now we can rewrite the matrices
as exponentials of the
generators it turns out that the
transpose of an exponential is just the
exponential of the transpose so we can
move this transpose operation to the
generator also recall that the
derivative of of an exponential just
gives us a factor of the generator out
in front because of chain
Rule now this formula must be true for
all values of theta so let's Sub in
theta equals 0 this causes all the
exponentials to go to the identity
Matrix this makes sense because a
rotation by 0 de is the
identity we're left with the generator
plus its transpose equaling the zero
Matrix
or in other words the transpose of the
generator equals the negative generator
so this proves that the generators of
SO3 matrices are
anti-symmetric now I want to give you a
warning about proofs that involve Matrix
exponentials if you wanted to try
proving that s SO3 generators are
anti-symmetric you might be tempted to
just Sub in these Matrix exponentials
and use exponent rules to add the
exponents together and use this to
conclude that the generator matrices are
anti-symmetric but this proof does not
work for an important
reason when exponentiating matrices we
cannot use the exponent rules we use for
numbers where we turn a product of
exponentials into the exponential of a
sum the reason for this is matrix
multiplication does not commute in
General and because of this the two
exponential formulas are not equal when
we expand them as an infinite series the
two formulas are only equal if the
generators
commute you can Google The Baker
Campbell hous door formula if you want
to learn more about
this in the case of an anti-symmetric
Matrix it does commute with its
transpose because we can move the minus
sign from one Matrix to the other so the
rule for turning a product of exponents
into the exponents of a sum does work
but we need to prove the two matrices
commute before we can use this
rule so we've proven that all SO3
generator matrices are traceless and
anti-symmetric now I said earlier that
these generator matrices are members of
a Lee algebra specifically the Lee
algebra so 3 but what does that mean
exactly remember an algebra is basically
a vector space where addition
subtraction and multiplication between
vectors is
defined we can Loosely think of these
generator matrices as being like
vectors just as we can add and subtract
vectors to get more vectors we can also
add and subtract generator matrices to
get more generator matrices when we we
add two traceless anti-symmetric
matrices together the result is also
traceless and
anti-symmetric so we know the result of
adding two s SO3 generators is another s
SO3
generator the same is true for
subtracting
generators but in an algebra we also
need to be able to multiply vectors
together you might assume the
multiplication rule between generators
is just matrix multiplication a but this
isn't quite correct the product of two
anti-symmetric matrices is not always
anti-
symmetric so the result of multiplying
two SO3 generators is not always another
s SO3 generator that is the exponential
of this product doesn't always give us a
rotation Matrix in
SO3 we can check this explicitly by
multiplying the XY generator with the y
z generator
we get this Matrix here this Matrix
actually squares to zero so when we
exponentiate it only the first couple
terms in the series are nonzero and we
get this which is not a rotation
Matrix however let's try something else
I'll multiply the generators XY and Y Z
and then subtract their product in the
opposite order y z * XY if we work
through the The Matrix multiplications
and subtract we get this Matrix which is
the ZX generator Matrix so it turns out
that when we multiply two generators in
either order and subtract the result we
get another
generator this operation on matrices is
called The Matrix
commutator and in the context of Lee
algebras it is often called the Lee
bracket this is what we will use as our
Vector multiplication rule rule in Lee
algebras since it's a way of combining
two generators to give us a third
generator if we work out all the
commutators for our rotation generators
we get these commutation relations here
this set of generators of the Le group
SO3 along with the rules for addition
subtraction and multiplication with the
Lee bracket form the Lee algebra
SO3 again Lee algebras are
conventionally written using lowercase
letters with a fractor
font in some more abstract books you
might see the Lee bracket defined like
this using the alternating and jacobe
properties instead but the Matrix
commutator satisfies both of these
properties so the Matrix commutator is a
valid Lee
bracket to discuss these SO3 commutation
Rel further I'm going to rewrite our SO3
generators as G1 G2 and
G3 now in a General Lee algebra when we
have a set of basis generators the Lee
bracket of two basis generators doesn't
always give us back another basis
generator however the Le bracket result
will always give us a linear combination
of basis
generators the coefficients in this
linear combination denoted f with
indices i j k are called the structure
coefficients for this lee
algebra if we look specifically at the
Lee algebra SO3 we can get the structure
coefficients by looking at the first
second and third Lee
brackets and then noting that the
commutator is
anti-symmetric so we get a sign change
when we swap the lower two indices of
the
coefficients all other coefficients are
zero this is sometimes summarized using
the antisymmetric symbol Epsilon also
called the Levi chiita
symbol now how do we know these
commutators will always give us a linear
combination of
generators to prove this I need to talk
about how a Lee algebra is like a
tangent space at the identity element of
its correspond lead
group remember a lead group is a group
that's continuous so it forms a
continuous curved space which is also
called a
manifold each point in this space would
be a different SO3 rotation
Matrix let's imagine that this curve in
our Le group space is a path containing
all the rotation matrices in the XY
plane that we get by increasing Theta
the point on this path where theta
equals 0 would be the identity Matrix
since a rotation by 0 de is the
identity when we take the derivative
with respect to Theta it's like we're
looking at the tangent vectors along
this curve and when we set Theta to zero
this means we're looking at the tangent
Vector specifically located at the
identity
element so the derivative at theta
equals 0 is a tangent Vector located at
the identity
Matrix so we can think of our generator
Matrix as being a tangent Vector at the
origin or identity of our Le group the
set of all generators is like a flat
space that's tangent to the Le group at
the identity keep in mind s SO3 is
actually a three-dimensional space with
three basis elements but I'm drawing it
as a 2d tangent plane just because
that's easier to
visualize now I'm going to use this idea
of paths in the curved Lee group space
to prove some properties about General
Lee
algebras so instead of dealing with Lee
group members that are rotations in SO3
parameterized by angles I'm going to
deal with General members of a general
Le Group Big G whose generators live in
the Lee algebra small
G I've taken these proofs from the
textbook naive Lee Theory by John
Stillwell first let's prove the sum of
two tangent vectors in a General Lee
algebra will give another tangent
Vector let's take group members a of S
and B ofs in the leag group Big G these
describe two paths in the lead Group
parameterized by S when s equals 0
both of these give the identity
transformation and their derivatives at
s equal 0 give their generators which
I'll write as small a and small
B if we multiply the group members a of
S and B of s we get a new group member C
of s let's take the derivative of both
sides and set s to zero on the right
side we use the product rule when we set
s to zero B of s and a of s just become
the identity element and when we look at
the derivatives at s equals 0 we get the
generators a plus b so we see the sum of
tangent vectors small a plus small B
gives another tangent Vector which is
the vector tangent to the curve C of s
at the
identity I'm going to make a small aside
here to explain the difference between a
generator and a tangent vector
I've already explained that with Matrix
exponentials the product of two Matrix
exponentials is not always equal to the
exponential of the sum however if we
expand these two formulas out as tailor
series it turns out that the first order
terms in both series are equal even
though the later terms in the series are
not equal this means that both of these
formulas have the same tangent Vector at
the identity
it's important to keep in mind that
there are an infinite number of possible
curves that go through the identity that
have the same tangent Vector at the
identity however when we're treating
this tangent Vector as a generator and
exponentiating it it only generates one
unique curve in the lead Group which is
the unique curve we get when we
exponentiate the tangent Vector
multiplied by a curve
parameter now let's prove the scalar
multiple of a tangent Vector gives
another tangent
Vector let's take the path a of s in the
group and multiply the parameter s by
some constant R to give us a of R * s
now let's take the derivative and set s
to zero using chain rule we get a factor
of R out in front and the derivative at
s equals 0 becomes the generator small a
so we see that the scalar multiple of
tangent Vector small a gives another
tangent Vector which is tangent to the
curve a of R *
s so we've shown that we can add tangent
vectors together and scale them to get
more tangent vectors this is the basic
definition of a vector space but to
prove that the set of tangent vectors
forms a Lee algebra we need to prove the
commutator of tangent vectors gives
tangent
Vector to prove this we'll look at a
path in the group Big G with three legs
a of s then B of T then a inverse of s
which takes us along the path a of s but
in the opposite direction we'll call
this path D of s and t and it has two
parameters this ABA inverse formula is
called a
conjugation if we take a con Conant s
and take the derivative with respect to
T the derivative only affects B of T
since a of s doesn't depend on T then if
we set T equals z we get the Lee algebra
generator small
B now let's take the derivative with
respect to S which gives us a product
rule on the right hand side if we set s
equal to zero both a of s and a inverse
of s go to the identity element
the derivative of a at zero becomes the
generator small a and the derivative of
a inverse at 0 is just the generator
that points in the opposite direction
which is small a so we get small a small
B minus small B small a which is the
commutator of small a and small
B now what exactly is this object on the
left hand side where we've taken the
derivative with respect to two different
parameters for constant s d of s and t
is just a path in the Le group that
depends on T and when we take the
derivative with respect to T and set T
to 0 this becomes a tangent Vector in
the tangent space located at tals
0 allowing s to vary every value of s
gives us a different tangent Vector in
the tangent space
so we get a continuous path of tangent
vectors parameterized by
S if we then take the derivative with
respect to S we get tangent vectors
along this path and setting s to zero
gives us the specific tangent Vector at
the
identity now since tangent vectors in a
vector space Also belong to that same
Vector space this tangent Vector at s
equal 0 also belongs to the tangent
space of of our original path in the Le
group at T equals
0 so all of that shows that the
commutator of two tangent vectors gives
another tangent Vector so the tangent
space of a leag group at the identity
does indeed form a Lee
algebra so let's review what we've
discovered so far about the Lee group
SO3 we found that each of the three
rotation matrices has a generator Matrix
and we can exponentiate the generator
times the angle to get the rotation
Matrix the two-step process for getting
these generators is to take the
derivative of the rotation Matrix and
then set the parameter to
zero using the algebraic properties of
matrices we found that the generators of
the SO3 Le group are the set of
traceless anti-symmetric
matrices we also proved that the
commutator of generators always gives a
member in the tangent space of
generators at the identity according to
these rules
here now let's repeat this process for
the lorence groupo
+13 this is the set of SpaceTime
Transformations that keep the space-time
interval with one plus sign and three
minus signs
unchanged the special s means the Matrix
determinant is + one and so spatial
Reflections are forbidden
the plus means the top left element of
the Matrix is positive and so time
Reflections are
forbidden this group includes three
rotation and three Lorent boost
matrices we can get the generators for
these matrices the usual Way by taking
the derivative and setting the parameter
to zero the rotation generators denoted
with J's are traceless and
anti-symmetric as we saw
before the Boost generators denoted with
Ks are traceless and
symmetric these six generators form a
basis for the Lee algebra s
+13 we can also work out the commutators
for these matrices to get these
commutation relations here this is the
Le bracket rule in the S so13 Lee
algebra note that the commutator of two
rotation generators gives a rotation
generator the commutator of two boost
generators also gives a rotation
generator and the commutator of a
rotation generator and a boost generator
gives a boost
generator this shows us that the S SO3
Le algebra lives inside the S so +13 Lee
algebra so in this video we've looked at
the Le groups s SO3 and S so +13 and
discovered their respective Lee
algebras but these Le group matrices
only operate on
vectors SO3 matrices operate on 3D space
vectors and S so plus 13 matrices
operate on 4D space-time
vectors since vectors are rank one
tensors we say these matrices are part
of the spin one
representation this helps us understand
how the spin one particles behave when
we do rot ations and
boosts but what about other particles
like the spin 1/2
particles this will be covered in the
next video where I cover the spin 1/2
representation which is one of the
multiple different representations of
the SO3 and S so +13 Lee
algebras if you've ever seen the complex
number I represented as a matrix that
squares to the negative identity you
might know that there are multiple
different matrices of all different
sizes that satisfy this
property the same is true for our Lee
algebra generators we've seen the 3X3
SO3 generator matrices and the 4x4 so
+13 generator
matrices these are from the spin one
representation because they transform
vectors however we can also find 2x two
matrices that follow the same Lee
algebra rules in both cases these are
from the spin 1/2 representation because
they transform
Spinners I'll go through all of this in
the next
video also one final note depending on
the textbook you read you might see that
the generators I've shown for rotations
and boosts look a little different
depending on whether they follow the
math convention or the physics
convention in this video I follow the
math convention where the generators of
3D rotation matrices are traceless and
anti-symmetric in the physics convention
it's often the case that the generators
are multiplied by netive I where I is
the imaginary unit this makes them
traceless and hermiss
matrices where Herm Mission means a
matrix equals its complex conjugate
transpose to compensate for this extra
Factor of minus I there needs to be an
additional factor of I with the opposite
sign used in the exponential to cancel
it
out physicists use this convention
because observables in quantum mechanics
must be represented by Herm Mission
operators which end up being the same
thing as Lee algebra
generators this hermiss property is
required so that observables like
momentum and spin always give real
numbers instead of complex
numbers in the case of rotations the
generators will be Herm mission in the
physics convention instead of
anti-symmetric as with the math
convention pure mathematicians don't
require this Herm Mission condition and
so they don't bother with these extra
factors of I in the generators or the
exponential
formula